Guide to the Records of the Albert Schweitzer Chair in the Humanities RG.21.1
New York University Archives
- Series IV: Student Papers
  - Undergraduate Papers (By Professor's Class): Ralph Ellison, undated; cuid5114 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225720 7
- Series V: Julian Mayfield Manuscripts
  The collectionof Mayfield manuscripts includes an early draft of his play "417" and his book The Meek Shall Not Inherit the Earth (Box 12). Mayfield's essay "Nicolo and the Prince in the White House" is located within the Public Lecture Series, and his correspondence while teaching at NYU may be found in the Program Files (Box 2, folder 7).
  - "417" (Drama), undated; cuid5115 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "The Meek Shall Not Inherit the Earth" (memoir), undated; cuid5116 (Box 12, Folder 5-8)
- Series VI: Lecture Series Recordings
  For more information see Series I: Program Files and Series III: Public Lectures.
  - Machiavelli and "The Prince", 1969 March 5; cuid4985 (Box 13, Reel cuid4985A, cuid4985B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4985A, RG21.1_cuid4985B)
    Lecturer: Grattan Freyer, academic, journalist, and potter.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Total duration: 111 min.
  - "Peace in the Middle East", 1969 March 6; cuid4986 (Box 13, Reel cuid4986A, cuid4986B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4986A, RG21.1_cuid4986B)
    Total duration: 71 min.
    Lecturer: Israeli Ambassador Yosef Tekoah, Permanent Representative of Israel to the UN (1968-1975).
    This lecture was sponsored by the NYU Institute of Hebrew Studies and GSO of the School of Education.
  - "Communist Power in Theory and Practice", 1969 March 12; cuid4987 (Box 13, Reel cuid4987A, cuid4987B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4987A, RG21.1_cuid4987B)
    Lecturers: Thompson Bradley, Professor of Russian Language and Literature from Swarthmore College; Jonathan Mirsky, Professor of Chinese Language and Literature from Dartmouth.
  - "White Power, Black Power--The Final Solutions", 1969 March 19; cuid4988 (Box 13, Reel cuid4988A, cuid4988B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4988A, RG21.1_cuid4988B)
    Total duration: 86 min.
    Lecturer: Julian Mayfield, visiting lecturer in Schweitzer program. American actor, director, writer, lecturer, and civil rights activist.
  - "Power and Ideas", 1969 March 26; cuid4989 (Box 13, Reel cuid4989A, cuid4989B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4989A, RG21.1_cuid4989B)
    Total duration: 74 min.
    Lecturer: NYU Philosophy Professor William Barrett.
  - "What Exhortation?--An Analysis of "The Prince" Chapter 26", 1969 April 23; cuid4990 (Box 13, Reel cuid4990A, cuid4990B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4990A, RG21.1_cuid4990B)
    Total duration: 101 min.
    Lecturer: NYU Professor and First Albert Schweitzer Chair Conor Cruise O'Brien.
  - Titled Reels: Gabriel Kolko (1 reel), 1968 February 13; cuid4991 (Box 13, Reel cuid4991, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4991)
    Duration: 91 min.
  - Unidentified Lectures and Other Recordings, 1968 April 10; cuid4992 (Box 13, Reel cuid4992, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4992)
    Duration: 99 min.
  - Titled Reels: Herbert Marcuse at NYU (3 reels), undated; cuid4993 (Box 13, Reel cuid4993A, cuid4993B, cuid4993C, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4993A, RG21.1_cuid4993B, RG21.1_cuid4993C)
    Duration: 84 min.
  - Titled Reels: U.S. and UN Seminar, Alger Hiss, 2 lectures (2 reels), undated; cuid4994 (Box 13, Reel cuid4994A, cuid4994B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4994A, RG21.1_cuid4994B)
    Duration: 227 min.
  - [Untitled experimental audio collage], undated; cuid4995 (Box 13, Reel cuid4995, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4995)
    The physical container is labeled "Language and symbolic action, D. Sherak for Ralph Ellison (1 reel)," but the recording contains an assortment of audio recordings from various sources, including a man reciting a Robert Frost poem and a discussion of Richard Strauss' "Also sprach Zarathustra."
    Total duration: 116 min.; Preservation note: "This is an experimental work recorded on four tracks, a combination of monaural and stereophonic recording methods. In total, four access files were created at the point of digitization. The digital access file ending in 000001 is a dual-mono configuration, believed to be the intended listening experience for tracks 1 and 3. The mono recordings for track 1 and 3 can also be listened to as separate tracks in the files ending in 000002 and 000003. Lastly, there is a stereophonic recording on tracks 2 and 4 that is available as 000003."
  - [Lectures from an NYU science symposium], Reel 1, undated; cuid4996 (Box 13, Reel cuid4996, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4996)
    Duration: 61 min.
    Lecture Topic 1: Sentinel ABM Missile Defense System; speaker is Professor Lustig. Lecture Topic 2: Opportunities for scientists in the late 1960s; speaker is Dr. David Z. Robinson, research physicist and NYU Vice President for Academic Affairs.
  - [Lectures from an NYU science symposium], Reel 2, undated; cuid4997 (Box 13, Reel cuid4997, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4997)
    Duration: 63 min.
    Lecture Topic 3: Social and political pressures facing U.S. scientists in the late 1960; speaker is Nicholas Unger. Followed by a panel Q&A (not complete recording).
  - [Untitled radio program about the Emancipation Proclamation], Reel 2 of 3, undated; cuid4998 (Box 13, Reel cuid4998B, Box Digitized Access Files, File RG21.1_cuid4998B)
    Duration: 28 min.; Preservation note: Only Tape B has content. The other two tapes are blank and were not digitized.
    This reel traces the origins of slavery in the U.S. and contains period music. Topics include: the Civil War, African Americans' participation in the Union Army, the rise of white nationalism.
- Series VII: Materials from Dean Hester, 1964-1970, 1983
  - Schweitzer Chair proposal, 1964; cuid5117 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - New York State Regents and NYU agreement, 1965; cuid5118 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Calls for nominations, 1964-1968, 1983; cuid5119 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Materials regarding Conor Cruise O'Brien, 1965-1966; cuid5120 (Box 14, Folder 4)